Preliminary Guide to the Robin Chandler Lynn Duke Papers, circa 1930-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robin Chandler Lynn Duke papers [ca. 1930]-2009
Duke, Robin Chandler Lynn
56.2 linear feet Extent: 81747 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robin Chandler Lynn Duke held office or was active in a number of organizations including Population Action International, the National Abortion Rights Action League, The Packard Foundation, the Draper World Population Fund, and several major corporations. Married to Ambassador Angier B. Duke. Collection (22100 items, dated 1942-2000) contains items related to Duke's extensive involvement in abortion rights, family planning, and population studies organizations. Series within the collection include correspondence, clippings, writings, publications, miscellaneous, photographs, and subject files. A substantial amount of correspondence from Duke was written to members of the U.S. House and Senate, and was written by Duke in her capacity as National Chair of Population Action International. Books and pamphlets report on population studies, child education, family planning, violence against women, and international education. Organizations represented in the collection include Population Action International, the Draper World Population Fund, Planned Parenthood, NARAL (National Abortion Rights Action League), "The Anatomy of Hate" conference, and the National Abortion Federation.
RL.00333
Language: English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Collection received starting in 1998.
Gifts include Accessions 2001-0147; 2001-0155; 2000-0341; 2002-0162; 2002-0311; 2003-0096; 2003-0268; 2005-0060; 2005-0120; 2006-062; 2006-0092; 2007-0014; 2007-0087; 2007-0194; 2008-0116; 2009-0168.
Biographical Note
Born in 1923, Duke held office or was active in a number of organizations including Population Action International, the National Abortion Rights Action League, The Packard Foundation, The Draper World Population Fund, and several major corporations. Her work continues to this day. She was married to Angier Biddle Duke, Chief of Protocol and ambassador to Spain and Denmark under the Kennedy and Johnson administration. She was also was ambassador to Norway.
Collection Overview
Collection (22100 items, dated 1942-2000) contains items related to Duke's extensive involvement in abortion rights, family planning, and population studies organizations. Series within the collection include correspondence, clippings, writings, publications, miscellaneous, photographs, and subject files. A substantial amount of correspondence from Duke was written to members of the U.S. House and Senate, and was written by Duke in her capacity as National Chair of Population Action International. Books and pamphlets report on population studies, child education, family planning, violence against women, and international education. Organizations represented in the collection include Population Action International, the Draper World Population Fund, Planned Parenthood, NARAL (National Abortion Rights Action League), "The Anatomy of Hate" conference, and the National Abortion Federation.
Additional organizations represented include the National Campaign to Prevent Teen Pregnancy, Promise Keepers, Rockefeller Foundation, Center for Gender Equality, Harvard School of Public Health, Friends of Art and Preservation in Embassies, Institute of International Education, International Flavors and Fragrances, National Mother's Day Committee, and the National Park Foundation.
Other parts of the collection deal more directly with Duke personally and with her husband. Files relate to social events and awards ceremonies, the Congressional campaign of 1977, and a number of other organizations concerned with her activities or her husband's ambassadorships. There is also information concerning the National Wildflower Research Center, the Council of American Ambassadors, the United Nations and other organizations; as well as information related to a white house dinner; speeches; articles about Duke; an appointment book; and personal files.
A number of other scrapbooks contain photos and other items from the time when Duke served as a fashion editor.
The addition (7089 items, 11.10 linear feet, dated ca. 1930-2001) comprises correspondence, subject files, articles and newspaper clippings, photographs, scrapbooks, photograph albums, and printed materials that primarily describe conferences attended and trips taken by Duke, focusing on the organizations in which she was actively involved. Also includes incoming and outgoing correspondence; files on fundraising dinners and meetings; and Angier Biddle Duke's typescript journal entries, For the Record (1981-1985), composed while visiting a number of countries. Also includes 71 black-and-white prints, 236 color prints, 780 color negatives, and 2 fabric bags. (01-147)
The addition (3250 items, 7.3 linear feet, dated 1960-2000) contains primarily correspondence, reports, speeches, newspaper clippings, printed material, and miscellaneous items related to Robin Duke's ambassadorship to Norway and her activism in major organizations for population control, including NARAL and Planned Parenthood. There are 5 videocassette tapes, including JFK--A Time Remembered; as well as 37 black-and-white and 5 color photographs, including a photograph album of a visit to Marrakech. The collection also contains diplomas, awards, and several commemorative photos/drawings signed by Lady Bird Johnson. (01-155)
The addition (2000-0341) (2175 items, 3.4 linear feet; dated 1991-2000 and undated, bulk 1998-2000) contains correspondence, notes, information packets, two videocassette tapes, one CD-RW containing 15 electronic audio file and printed material from meetings Duke attended. Also includes correspondence, speech notes, two black-and-white photographs, and information packets relating to the Albert Lasker Public Service Award Duke won in 1991. There is one additional black-and-white group photograph taken at a lecture.
The addition (2002-0162) (2400 items, 4.0 linear feet; dated [ca. 1990]-2002) contains primarily reports, printed material, correspondence, and 1 black-and-white and 12 color photographs related to Duke's activism in various organizations, including Friends of Art and Preservation in Embassies and the US-Japan Foundation (1990-2001). Also includes correspondence, orientation packets, talking points, and reports received or used by Duke as ambassador to Norway (2000-2001).
The addition (2002-0311) (750 items, 1.6 linear feet) comprises miscellaneous materials relating to Duke's numerous involvements, including personal and professional correspondence, meeting and event information, organizational files, newspaper clippings, reports, and printed material. A container list was not created for this addition.
The addition (2003-0096) (1500 items, 2.2 linear feet) contains correspondence and other materials related to Duke's activism in organizations including F.A.P.E., A.S.F., I.R.C., and the U.N. Association (1983-2003); and documents related to her position as Ambassador to Norway (2000-2001). Also includes files about parties and other events, and a small amount of personal correspondence.
The addition (2003-0268) (500 items, 1.4 lin. ft.; dated 1998-2003) contains business correspondence and other materials related to Duke's activism in NARAL, UNESCO, and Population Action International. Also includes a small amount of personal correspondence and 2 VHS tapes, Packing the Courts: The Battle over President Bush's Judicial Appointments and Access Denied: US Family Planning Restrictions in Zambia.
The addition (2005-0060) (3390 items, 5.4 lin. ft.; dated 2002-2005) comprises correspondence, printed material, and board meeting packets related to Duke's activism. Also includes a transcript of oral history interviews conducted by Smith College, and 3 VHS videocassettes.
The addition (2005-0120) (697 itmes, 1.8 lin. ft.; dated 1992-2005) comprises personal and professional correspondence; board meeting packets related to Duke's activism in a wide variety of organizations.
The addition (2006-0054) (576 items; 1.3 lin. ft.; dated 1969-2006 and undated) contains correspondence (1993-2006); and other materials related to Duke's activism. There are also 2 CD-ROMs, printed material, clippings, and invitations to luncheons and dinner parties.
The addition (2006-0062) (1025 items; 1.6 lin. ft.; dated 1962-2006 and undated) comprises correspondence, invitations, speeches, printed material, and ephemera related to Duke's activism in organizations (1983-2006). There are also materials that once formed a photo album/scrapbook, with 27 black-and-white photos of the Dukes as well as interior and exterior photos documenting their remodeling of Blair House, the presidential guest quarters, in Washington, DC (undated, probably 1962); invitations; and correspondence (1962-1968), including letters from Jackie Kennedy, Lady Bird Johnson, and others.
The addition (2006-0092) (1025 items; 1.6 lin. ft.; dated 1962-2006 and undated) contains clippings, periodicals and reference works, as well as meeting guides, conference materials, correspondence and other materials regarding Duke's political, charitable and ambassadorial activities. There is also one DVD and two black-and-white copies of family photos.
The addition (2007-0014) (1500 items; 2.4 lin. ft.; dated 1962-2006) contains correspondence, including letters from Jackie Kennedy and Lady Bird Johnson; menus and programs for United States Presidential luncheons and dinners; documentation, pamphlets, and files from councils and organizations; a diploma for Angier Biddle Duke from Duke University; speeches; printed materials; and newspaper clippings.
The addition (2007-0087) (675 items; 0.9 lin. ft.; dated 1964-2007) contains correspondence, photographs, speech transcripts, and conference materials from Duke's charitable and political organizations.
The addition (2007-0194) (675 items; 0.9 lin. ft; dated 2000-2007) contains correspondence, charitable committee and meeting materials, and a New York Look Book featuring Duke and her fashion sense. This collection has been interfiled with Addition (2007-0087).
The addition (2008-0116) (600 items; 0.8 lin. ft; dated 2007-2008) includes conference ephemera and other materials from Duke's involvement in charities and political activities; miscellaneous materials and correspondence; and publications from various international organizations.
Addition (2009-0168) (900 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1960s-2009) includes correspondence, board meeting publications from Duke's various charities and organizations, letters from prominent people, and miscellaneous materials such as newspaper clippings and photographs.
Subject Headings
Duke, Robin Chandler Lynn; Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995; National Abortion Rights Action League; Population Action International; Planned Parenthood Federation of America; Draper World Population Fund; National Abortion Federation (U.S.); United Nations; David & Lucille Packard Foundation; American-Scandinavian Foundation; International Rescue Committee; Friends of Art and Preservation in Embassies (U.S.); Birth control-United States-History-20th century; Abortion -- United States; Abortion-Government policy-United States; Population policy; Women's rights; Diplomatic etiquette; Ambassadors -- United States; Videocassettes; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Color negatives; Clippings; CD-ROM; Machine-readable records
Contents of Collection
- Accessions (1998-0310) and (1998-0311)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Asking Money, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Faxes, January 1997 (Box 1)
    - Faxes, November 1997 (Box 1)
    - General, 1970s (Box 1)
    - General, 1980s (Box 1)
    - General, 1990 (Box 1)
    - General, 1994 (Box 1)
    - General, 1995 (Box 1)
    - General, 1996 (Box 1)
    - General, 1997 (Box 1)
    - General, 1998 (Box 1)
    - General, undated (Box 1)
    - Important Letters (Box 1)
    - Personal, September 1996 (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Personal, January 1997 (Box 1)
    - Personal, April 1997 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Personal, August 1997 (Box 1)
    - Personal, October 1997 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Personal, December 1997-January 1998 (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Personal, ca. 1997-1998 (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - Abortion, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Abortion (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - Blair House (Box 1)
    - Gun Control (Box 1)
    - Personal (Box 1)
    - Population Crisis Committee (Box 1)
    - Publicity and Interviews (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - General, 1960s (Box 1)
    - General, 1970s (Box 1)
    - General, 1980 (Box 1)
    - General, 1981 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - General, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
    - General, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - General, 1989 (Box 1)
    - General, 1990 (Box 1)
    - General, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - General, 1994 (Box 1)
    - General, 1995 (Box 1)
    - General, 1996 (Box 1)
    - General, 1997 (Box 1)
    - General, undated (Box 1)
  - Subject Files (Box 2)
    - Afghanistan, Ambassador's Ball, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Africa, Remarks by Hilary Rodham Clinton (Box 2)
    - Alan Guttmacher Institute (Box 2)
    - Ambassadors' Orientation (Box 2)
    - American Home Products Inc., Annual Reports (Box 2)
    - Appointment Book, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Art Pro Choice (Box 2)
    - Barnard College, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Birmingham-Southern College, GALA 1989 (Box 2)
    - Book Notes (Box 2)
    - Cairo, 1994 (ICPD Prep.) (Box 2)
    - Center for Reproductive Law and Policy (Box 2)
    - Chief of Mission Administrative Briefing Paper, Morocco, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Council of American Ambassadors, Board of Directors Meeting, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - Council of American Ambassadors, Business Meeting, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Council of American Ambassadors, Membership Directory, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Council of Foreign Relations - Conference on Nigeria, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Draper World Population Fund Report, 1977-1986 (Box 2)
    - Duke Family Calendar (Box 2)
    - East River Savings Bank, ERSB - News Releases (Box 2)
    - Female Genital Mutilation (Box 2)
    - Friends of Art and Preservation in Embassies, FAPE (Box 2)
    - Friends of Art and Preservation in Embassies, FAPE, Board Meeting 1997 (Box 2)
    - Harvard School of Public Health (Box 2)
    - Helsinki (Box 2)
    - Horizons (Box 2)
    - Household Inventory, Ambassador's Residence, Rabat Morocco, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Institute of International Education (Box 2)
    - International Conference on Population and Development (Box 2)
    - International Flavors and Fragrances, Inc. - Annual Reports (Box 2)
    - International Planned Parenthood Federation - Publications (Box 2)
    - International Women's Health Coalition (Box 2)
    - Itineraries (Box 2)
    - Margaret Sawyer Award, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Message Log, June 5, 1981 and undated (Box 2)
    - Message Log, Dec. 4 and Dec. 16, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Memoranda and Statistics (Box 2)
    - NARAL, Roe v. Wade 25th Anniversary (Box 2)
    - NARAL, Tribute to Robin Chandler Duke, 1989 (Box 2)
    - NARAL, 20th Anniversary, 1989 (Box 2)
    - NARAL, Miscellaneous (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - National Campaign to Prevent Teen Pregnancy (Box 3)
    - National Center for Children in Poverty (Box 3)
    - National Institute of Social Sciences Awards Dinner (Box 3)
    - National Women's Economic Alliance (Box 3)
    - NWRC - National Women's Resource Center - Letters and Memos (Box 3)
    - NWRC - National Women's Resource Center - Objectives (Box 3)
    - Packard Foundation, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Packard Foundation Board of Trustees Meeting, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Packard Foundation Board of Trustees Meeting, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Packard Foundation Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Packard Foundation Population Committee Meeting, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Pakistan, Population Work, Oct.- Nov. 1976 (Box 3)
    - Packwood, Sen. Robert, Breakfast, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Packwood, Sen. Robert, Dinner, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Philippines, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Photograph, Robin Chandler Duke, Moscow 1959. (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Advertisements (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, April 29, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Bylaws (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, The Justice Fund (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Letters (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Baltimore, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Cleveland, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Los Angeles (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Louisville, KY, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, NYC, Benny Goodman Benefit, May 2, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, NYC, Letters and Memos (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, NYC, New York Times Tearsheets (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Southeastern Pennsylvania, March 1983 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, South Palm Beach (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Tennessee, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Vermont, May 1981 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Washington D.C., 1979 (Box 3)
    - Planned Parenthood, Westchester, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, 1996, Dec. (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, 1997, Feb. (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Board of Directors (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Board of Directors Meeting, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, TV - "To the Contrary" (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Publications (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Publications (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Population Crisis Committee (Box 4)
    - Population Crisis Committee, Board Meeting 1991 (Box 4)
    - Population Health Imperatives (Box 4)
    - Pro-Choice Resource Center - Opposition Primer 1996 (Box 4)
    - Publications, Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Qatar, 1980, Oct. (Box 4)
    - Rockefeller, John D., 3rd. (Box 4)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson (Box 4)
    - Rockwell International, Inc., Annual Reports (Box 4)
    - Rusk, Dean. - Dinner, 75th Birthday Celebration (Box 4)
    - Sasakawa Funeral (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook - "Robin Duke Runs for the U.S. Congress - 1977" (Box 4)
    - Spanish Institute, Annual Report, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
    - Speech Materials (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Speeches, 1977-1981 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Speeches, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Speeches and Biography for Duke University (Box 4)
    - Speeches Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Tokyo Symposium (Box 4)
    - Tolstoy Foundation (Box 4)
    - Tolstoy, May 29, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Trip to China (Box 4)
    - UNFPA (Box 4)
    - United Nations Association, 1997 (Box 4)
    - United Nations Association, 1998 (Box 4)
    - United Nations Population Fund (Box 4)
    - United States-Japan Foundation, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Women's Equity Action League (Box 4)
- Accessions (1998-0350) and (1998-0372)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1996, Sept. - 1997, Nov. (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Population Crisis Committee, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Population Crisis Committee, 1992 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Population Action International, 1993 (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - Population Action International, 1994 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Population Action International, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Population Action International, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Robin Duke and Al Fore, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1989-1990 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Personal, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Photographs of the Angier B. Duke Family (Box 1)
  - Subject Files (Box 2)
    - Abortion Articles (Box 2)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 2)
    - American Home Products, Inc. - Questionnaires (Box 2)
    - American Home Products, Inc. - Proxy Statement, 1996 (Box 2)
    - American Home Products, Inc. - Annual Report, 1997 (Box 2)
    - American Inst. for Public Service, Board Meeting, 1994 (Box 2)
    - American Inst. for Public Service - Jefferson Award Nominations, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Biddle - Promissory Note (Box 2)
    - Bosnia Diary of Robin C. Duke (Box 2)
    - Boys Harbor, Inc. (Box 2)
    - Cairo 1994 (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Center for Reproductive Law and Technology - Janet Benshoof (Box 2)
    - Centre for Development and Population Activities (Box 2)
    - Duke University - Duke University and the Independent World (Box 2)
    - Earth Times Clippings (Box 2)
    - Friends of Art and Preservation in Embassies - FAPE (4 folders) (Box 2)
      Board meetings and miscellaneous.
    - Guttmacher Institute (Box 2)
    - Hastings Center (Box 2)
    - Horizon Communications (Box 2)
    - ICPD - International Conference on Population Control, 1993 (Box 2)
    - International Conference on Population, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Japan Trip, April 1993 (Box 2)
    - Keystone Center, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Lasker Medical Research Awards (Box 2)
    - Lists - Various functions and organizations (Box 2)
    - Loeb Awards, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Margaret Sanger Film (Box 2)
    - NARAL (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Open Mind - 1996 (Box 2)
    - Packard Foundation - 1989 (Box 2)
    - Packard Foundation - David Packard (Box 2)
    - Packard Foundation - Population Committee Meeting, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Planned Parenthood Foundation - Board Meeting, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Population Action International, Miscellaneous (7 folders) (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Board Meeting, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Board of Directors Meeting, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Governance Committee Meeting, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Governance Committee Meeting, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Governance Committee Meeting, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Governance Committee Meeting, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Population Action International, Governance Committee Meeting, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Population Council - Margaret Catley-Carson (Box 3)
    - Population Crisis Committee (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Population Crisis Committee (Box 3)
      Staff Directory, Schedule, Board of Directors list.
    - RU-486 (Box 3)
    - Southampton Press (Box 3)
    - UN Conference on Environment and Development, 1991 (Box 3)
    - UNFPA Award Nominations, 1996 (Box 3)
    - U.S.-Japan Foundation (3 folders) (Box 3)
      Korea trip (1998), miscellaneous.
    - World Affairs Council, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Writings
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Box 3)
    - Speech Materials and Notes (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Publications
    - The Global 2000 Report to the President: Entering the 21st Century (Box 3)
    - JAMA - Oct. 2, 1991, (v. 266 n. 13) (Box 3)
- Accession (1999-0157)
  - Subject Files, A-P (Box 1)
  - Subject files, R-W (Box 2)
  - Professional Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials (Box 2)
  - Publications (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Committee and Conference Materials (Box 3)